Guide to the Andrews Family Collection 1825-1913 MS 005 MS 005 MS 005
Cornwall Historical Society
Andrews Family Collection
1825-1913
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 005
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
This collection consists of documents relating to the Andrews family of Cornwall. The Andrews family produced several influential clergymen, and this collection reflects the interests of Cornwall town historian E.C. Starr, himself a Congregationalist minister. Starr gathered the items found in this collection and used much of the information in his book, A History of Cornwall, Connecticut: A Typical New England Town.
Provenance
This collection reflects the interests of Cornwall town historian E.C. Starr, himself a Congregationalist minister. Starr gathered the items found in this collection and used much of the information in his book, A History of Cornwall, Connecticut: A Typical New England Town.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
"Most of the items in this collection are associated with the family of Reverend William Andrews (1782-1838). Andrews was a native of Ellington, Connecticut and moved to Cornwall in 1827 when he agreed to become pastor of the First Church. In addition to the elder Reverend Andrews, the collection also contains documents related to his sons, William Watson Andrews (1810-1897), Edward Warren Andrews (1811-1895), Israel Ward Andrews (1815-1888), Samuel James Andrews (1817-1906), Timothy Langdon Andrews (1819-1908), and Ebenezer Baldwin Andrews (1821-1880). All of these sons, except for Timothy Langdon Andrews, who worked as a physician, served as ministers at various times.William Given Andrews (1835-1912) was the son of William Watson Andrews, and similarly entered the ministry. Starr also included John T. Andrew (1811-1887) in this collection, despite his lack of relation to the Andrews family. Andrew was a Yale graduate who owned a Cornwall farm and served as vice president of the National Agricultural Society."
Scope and Content Note
The collection is organized generationally into three series.
Arrangement
The collection is organized generationally into series then chronologically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
First Generation
Second Generation
Third Generation
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Correspondence; obituaries; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Andrews, William (1782-1838)
- First Generation
  - William Andrews
    - Sermon on the "Song of Solomon", 1825 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Funeral sermon delivered by Rev. Grant Powers, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - William Watson Andrews
    - Religious Publications, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 3-19)
    - Editorials, 1889-1894; , undated (Box 1, Folder 20-27)
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, regarding genealogy and childhood memories of Cornwall, 1890-1897; , undated (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1894-1895 (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
    - Obituaries, 1897-1900; , undated (Box 1, Folder 35-42)
  - Edward Warren Andrews
    - Independence Day Oration, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Receipt of Frederick Kellogg, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
    - Obituary, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Second Generation
  - Israel Ward Andrews
    - Publications, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 1-26)
    - List of publications, undated; , 1888 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Letter sent to Frederick Kellogg, regarding the Civil War, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Letter sent to Frederick Kellogg, regarding a library book, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Obituaries and memorials, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from Marietta College regarding I.W. Andrews, 1893; , undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Note by E.C. Starr about vital records of I.W. Andrews, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Signature of I.W. Andrews, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Samuel James Andrews
    - Publications, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 34-57)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr about locations in Cornwall, 1891-1906; , undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr about donating books to the library, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Book reviews of works by S.J. Andrews, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 60-61)
    - Fiftieth wedding anniversary announcement for S.J. Andrews and Catherine Andrews, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Obituaries and tributes, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 63-66)
- Third Generation
  - Timothy Langdon Andrews
    - Publications, 1888-1892 (Box 3, Folder 1-33)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, about sending him newspaper clippings, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, about reminisces of Cornwall, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Ebenezer Baldwin Andrews
    - Autographs, 1859; , undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Publications, 1860-1879 (Box 3, Folder 37-46)
    - Obituary, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Biographical sketch, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr from Mrs. E.B. Andrews, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - William Given Andrews
    - Oration, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr about family information, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Obituary, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Obituary and biography, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - John T. Andrew
    - Photo, with biographical notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)